My topic is fixing Stable Diffusion
VAE's spurious bright pixels
The core idea of this project is very simple
To solve the tiny imperfections
known as spurious bright pixels
caused by VAEs when generating images using Stable Diffusion
What are VAE's spurious bright pixels?
When we generate images from Stable Diffusion
we need VAE decoder to reconstruct
the normal image from the latent image
Because diffusion models generate
latent images in a highly compressed dimension
Lots of high-frequency detail
can only be reconstructed
by the distribution learned from the training data
CFG is a parameter to control
how much the model
follows the text prompt
The higher the CFG
the more the model influences
the generation direction from the text prompt
However the text prompt
can only offer limited semantic information
it lacks lots of detail or features
from the real image
When CFG is too high
the latent may be pulled
out of the distribution
trained from the training data
When the VAE decoder receives this
out of distribution extreme latent values
it cannot reconstruct the normal image stably
and then conduct local output saturation
or abnormal highlight values
In the final image
these abnormal values
will appear as a few bright spots
or pixels that are off-color pixels
known as spurious bright pixels or impulse noise
These artifacts not only appear in
dark or high contrast
or high contrast areas
but usually are observed in these areas
due to high bright contrast
Because these artifacts usually
come from
a few abnormal latents
it usually has only 1 to 5 pixel size
in a 1k image
Next I will introduce three related solutions
Repaint represents diffusion model patching
PatchMatch represents block texture synthesis
and the Telea FMM represents boundary diffusion
The first method is Repaint
Its core mechanism is to use a mask
to divide the image to be repaired
into known regions and unknown regions
During the denoising process
for known regions
the original image is directly supplemented
with noise at the corresponding time step
Unknown regions undergo normal denoising
The two are stitched together
after this denoising step
To ensure a natural stitch
the image is resampled to the previous step
and denoised again after stitching
Furthermore
to allow the model to more effectively
integrate semantic information
through the denoising process
Repaint introduces the concept of jump lengths
By repeatedly performing forward and reverse
operations across multiple time steps
it improves the harmony and semantic
plausibility of the final image
While this is a powerful method
I believe it is not suitable for the
current situation
Running 250 to 1000 diffusion steps
for a 1 to 5 pixel defect
requiring 8 to 12 GB of GPU memory
and with latency in the seconds
to minutes range is not worthwhile
The second method we will be looking at
today is PatchMatch
To begin
the algorithm covers the target area
the region we want to inpaint
using a sliding window to extract patches
of a specified size
Initially
these patches are randomly paired with patches
of the exact same size
from the available source image
Next we enter the iterative
optimization phase
which is the core of this algorithm
This phase consists of two alternating steps
First propagation
For every patch in the target area
the algorithm checks the matching
results of its immediate neighbors
If a neighbor's offset provides a better match
meaning the source patch it points to
is more similar
the current patch simply adopts
or copies that neighbor's offset
Second random search
Taking the currently matched patch's
location in the source image
as a center point
the algorithm performs random sampling
within a specified radius
This search radius gradually shrinks
allowing the algorithm to fine-tune
and find the best local optimum
These two steps propagation and random search
are continuously repeated
The loop stops either when it reaches
a predefined maximum number of iterations
or when it fully converges meaning the
matching results stop changing
Ultimately
this iterative process generates
a complete look-up table
mapping every single patch in the target area
to its best matching patch in the source image
Now for the final reconstruction
Because the sliding window overlaps
each individual pixel in the target area
will have multiple patches overlapping it
To resolve this
the algorithm uses a voting mechanism
It looks at the corresponding pixels from all
the matched source patches and essentially votes
or averages them out to determine
the most appropriate final color for the
specified pixel
To summarize its application
this method is incredibly well suited
for large
scale object removal and complex
texture reconstruction
Moreover
its speed is significantly faster compared
to the previous method we discussed
However
as I mentioned earlier
PatchMatch is primarily designed for
large-area inpainting
If we are only trying to fix minor
microscopic blemishes
running a full-image search using this method
is not only a waste of computational resources
but it also risks
pulling in irrelevant textures from other
parts of the image
The third method is the Telea FMM
First the algorithm
divides the image into three regions based
on the mask provided by the user
The gray known region
the white unknown region
and the red boundary separating the two regions
Next the algorithm traces along the boundary
to find the outermost ring of pixels inside the hole
This is called band 0 and it is the
very first area to be inpainted
Starting from band 0
the algorithm traverses inward visiting each pixel
and recording its corresponding arrival time
This time serves as a reference for
the inpainting sequence
After calculating the order of every pixel
the inpainting process begins from band 0
which has the earliest arrival time
Theoretically
every time a pixel is inpainted
its neighbors' arrival times are updated
and the pixel with the next earliest
arrival time is chosen for the next round
In actual implementation however
the algorithm first computes the arrival
times for all pixels
and then carries out the inpainting sequentially
For a target point p to be inpainted
the algorithm looks at all known neighboring
points q within a specified radius
For each neighbor q
it uses a first-order approximation
to estimate what color point p should be
as if extending from q to p
Then a weight is calculated based on
three factors
the direction from q to p
the geometric distance and the level set
corresponding to the arrival time
Once the color predictions and weights
from all points q are calculated
they are combined using a weighted average
to get the final color to fill into point p
When all pixels are inpainted in this
calculated order
we get the fully restored image
Because this algorithm doesn't search
through the entire image
but instead only looks at the pixels
near the hole and fills it in what using surrounding colors
it is very fast and highly suitable for
filling small gaps
This makes it a perfect fit for the problem
we are trying to solve right now
Next I would like to introduce my project
The system workflow is broken down
into three main steps
First we identify candidate pixels using
a combination
of the Laplace operator and median residual
utilizing brightness as our threshold
to eliminate false positives and obtain
a highly precise mask
We then filter the results through connected
component analysis and variance filtering
Second
the precise mask is passed to the
Telea FMM method
for the actual image inpainting
Third
we provide a graphical user interface
featuring a red mask preview
This allows for real-time parameter adjustments
and even gives users the ability to manually
edit the mask themselves
However
developing this system comes with a few
key challenges
The first challenge is legitimate
bright details and actual artifacts
can sometimes look nearly identical
making them extremely difficult to
distinguish from one another
The second challenge is that
noise doesn't always manifest as a highly
prominent bright spot
Sometimes it appears as subtle
solid-color blobs
that just look like out of place compared
to their surroundings
And the third challenge is thin, long natural structures
such as strands of hair or fine lines
possess extremely high local contrast
and sharpness
Because of this
local gradient detection algorithms can easily
misidentify fragments of these sharp
natural details as isolated noise
That concludes my presentation
Thank you for listening